great so this is Mike L on um Wednesday
May
8th from home it looks like I'm I'm at
home today yeah yeah me too me too well
I thought this sales piece was
absolutely fascinating just oh thank you
fireworks of ideas coming off it just
very rich um so I'd love to ask you a
few questions about it just to unpack it
and then we can take it from there um
first of all connect this thinking and
this piece to your lab work what what
what brought you to this these thoughts
and what yeah what were you seeing that
made you want to answer the questions
you answer in this piece yeah great
question uh let's see a couple of things
first um I am really interested in
information and how information is is
used by different components of the
living body so you know Josh Josh
bongard and I have been developing this
notion of polyc computing which is this
idea that basically every subcomponent
is hacking every other subcomponent in
the sense that it doesn't know or care
what the original intent of the message
was it's going to interpret it as best
as it can how you know however it can
when you say it are you talking about
organisms you what are you talking about
well all every every level so cells
subcellular protein networks Pathways
organs tissues you know anils every
every everything right I think I think
this is a fundamental feature of biology
that it's a hacker in that sense that
that you have no allegiance to how
something was intended to be used you're
going to do the best you can in
interpreting what and and and and that
comes from from some you know working
with Josh bongard with with his um
discoveries that the exact same physical
mechanism can be seen by one Observer to
be Computing one function and another
Observer to be be Computing a different
function so that that right that when
when you ask you know what is this
physical process Computing somebody
might say well I know what it is I wrote
the algorithm so I can tell you what it
is but in by biology nobody cares who
wrote the algorithm well yeah well I
don't care what you say I'm interpreting
your your algorithm your novel your
message in my own way whatever I I you
know it doesn't matter to me what what
you think you meant by it I get whatever
I get out of it is what I get out of it
right so so uh anyway so so it's so it
starts with that and and attempts to
understand how different uh biological
systems uh interpret information and I
was thinking
uh okay so that's one thing the second
thing thing is I I really think that
there is a lot of important work to be
done to Break um binary categories that
we naively think exist but actually are
just hiding a lot of um limits on our
imagination and so this this notion of
data to data versus the machine that
operates on that data and this idea that
information is passive and then you have
this active uh a cognitive being
whatever it is that's going to operate
on that data remember it you know store
it change it you you know what whatever
and so so I so I was thinking about um
ways that that we could we could break
that and really make that into a
Continuum and I was thinking about the
whole but caterpillar butterfly thing
and I thought about this for for for you
know many many years uh and the
originally the thing you might think is
cool about it is the question of where's
the information because the brain gets
mostly refactored okay but then it hit
me I was I was literally I was I was
taking a walk with with my dad and it
and it and I was thinking about this and
it hit me that that isn't the most
interesting part here what's interesting
is that the
actual the the the details of the
information that the butter that the
caterpillar learns are actually quite
useless to the butterfly because it's
going to have to remap all of it onto a
completely different body with different
priorities it doesn't care about leaves
anymore it you know it lives in
threedimensional world like all of that
has to get remapped and so immediately I
sort of I sort of realized that what's
going on here is is is the what's
preserved across lifetimes from from
that caterpillar to that butterfly is
not the f it of the information it's the
it's a kind of um inferred salience it's
it's what does this mean to me and that
what's actually passed on physically
some sort of engram we don't know what
it is it could be an RNA like a glanc
says what's an engram would you define
that term for me yeah an engram is just
a it's a it's a physical embodiment of a
memory so so it's it's anything in your
brain or body that uh stores information
and all that means is that there is some
Observer later on meaning a cell a
tissue the whole animal or or a
scientist or somebody else who's going
to then look at that physical object and
say oh look I know what this means this
is going to interpret this as as as as a
memory and so you know ant ants is DNA
in engram or not yeah I think so yeah
okay yeah yeah I think so but now now
again that that requires that requires a
real shift I think most biologists would
say no but I think it is because I think
that um all memories are just messages
from your past self and that what's
happening with DNA is that previous
previous basically there's this giant
lineage agent that's the scale of an
evolutionary lineage and the DNA are its
engrams where that information is is
being passed on the way that any memory
would and much like these other memories
it's up for interpretation which is why
you have this this incredible
flexibility of forms yeah you've got the
same DNA but if you're a salamander and
I changed the number of cells or the
size of cells or or you know do all this
other crazy stuff you can still make
things work because you don't interpret
you take it seriously but not literally
that
information so right so yeah so so going
back to the butterfly yeah yeah yeah so
so the engrams right um that uh that
that are left there are to be
interpreted
and that leads to this this question of
uh and again the reason so get get back
to your original question what does it
mean for our lab work because because
what we would like to do is communicate
with effectively communicate with the
different parts of the biology I mean
what we do is we communicate with cells
tissues and organs for regenerative
medicine applications some people are
going to want to communicate with
ecosystem somebody else is going to want
to communicate with you know uh uh so
social structures or or financial
structures I don't know what and so so
we're interested in asking how does you
know by by understanding how does a
persistent agent a self maintain itself
um over time you can learn something
about how do we communicate with it so
we would like to rewrite those memories
and we would like to say if there's a
birth defect or there's a uh some kind
of traumatic injury or something and we
want the cells to build something else
we really need to understand how these
memories are interpreted so that's why
yeah that's that's that's why this this
is of relevance to us so in the
butterfly
case would you say there is a self
that's continuous from from caterpillar
to butterfly so so here's what I think
we ought to do with this and this is by
no means a new a new idea this is this
is kind of just process philosophy in
many made made more practical in many
ways um you know there's a there's an
old Paradox and and I'm trying to figure
out who first said it I I thought it was
biton but I could be wrong but but
somebody had this Paradox that said if
if a species fails to change then it
will no doubt eventually go extinct if
it does change then again it's not the
same species and so again it's gone so
what do you what do you do what's the
right what can you do that's the Paradox
and and that same Paradox is
um it's it's it's it's the same thing
with with us because in a certain sense
if you if you insist on a definition of
the self that is a permanent structure
it's a thing then you've got the same
Paradox because if I mature if I learn
if I expand if I you know any of those
things I'm no longer me and that's scary
and at some point you know is the child
that you once were still here I mean in
many ways no right so that's a that's a
problem but I think I think the answer
both on the personal case and the uh
evolutionary case is that what we need
to do is Define the self as a continuous
construction of sense making so it's a
process it's not a single thing it's a
so so that part isn't new plenty plenty
of people have said that but but I I
think the new thing is to understand
exactly what it's doing what I think
it's doing is constantly trying to make
sense of its own memories so every and I
don't know how what 300 milliseconds you
know in a human I don't know what it
what it would be exactly but you you
don't have access to your past what you
have access to is the engrams left by
your past you have the messages from
your past celf so this constant process
of trying to make sense of what do my
what do these chemical um Messengers
mean if it's RNA or it's prot you know
whatever uh synaptic structures whatever
it's going to be uh what do they mean
can I can I Cobble together a coherent
story of myself my past my environment
and be creative about it the the the the
thing the the other thing that hit me
that's I think really cool about this is
that um uh and we could talk later about
this this bow tie business but but in
any case what's happening is you have
you have a bunch of experiences and you
don't memorize the details you have to
squeeze them down you have to compress
them into some sort of a inference a
generative you know a model that's of of
everything that happened right so uh
when you when it comes time to to
interpret this thing to recall the
memory because because it's compressed
you have to sort of reinflated it and
you have to make it make sense for your
new environment maybe you you're
physically you've changed or whatever
you have to you have to reinl it but the
thing is that good compression always
looks like randomness you know this is
something that the seti people uh point
out that that a really Advanced signal
is going to look maximally random
because because when you compress lots
of particulars into a general rule you
the whole point of compression is is to
throw out all the correlations anything
that's correlated you can get rid of it
because you can comp you know you can
compress it out but once you've done all
of that what you have looks really
random and so that means that on the
interpretation end when you look at
these molecules or synaptic structures
or whatever it is in order to uh figure
out what they mean you can't deduce it
in a deductive algorithm because the
information isn't there it's been it's
been stripped off you have to be
creative it's it's more it's more
creativity and uh you know um um maybe
what people call intuition I don't know
but it's but it's much more of a you you
have to bring something to it you can't
just read exactly what it says because
right it's sparse there's not there's
very little
there why now tell me exactly why do you
have to
compress you have to compress bandwidth
question
well because because if you don't
compress all learning is about
compression because because if you don't
compress then what you've done is what
what the machine science machine
learning folks call um overtraining
you've you've you've memorized a bunch
of particulars and if and and if you're
a very simple organism in a very
simplified environment that might even
be okay but but normally the whole point
of learning is you learn a rule you
don't remember there were these pixels
on my retina then there were those
pixels on my R you don't remember that
what you remember is this General thing
leads to this other General thing right
you remember these these connections
abstracting exactly that's what it is
it's generalization and abstraction
that's exactly and that seems to me
what's happened in the caterpillar
butterfly case right I mean so in the
experiment that you describe it wasn't I
realized it wasn't yours though it was
somebody else's experiment yeah yeah
yeah it's not it's not my experiment it
was done it was first done in the 70s um
by a bunch of Russian groups who did uh
um larv Beetle and things like that and
then it was done by uh Doug Blackiston
who is actually a staff scientist in my
center but but he did this work when he
was younger and uh yeah he did it with
moth caterpillar to moths and he did it
there was some training some Operating
Conditioning going on right to associate
food with a certain color yep and so the
abstraction there or the result of the
compression was concept food right
rather than specific leaf or nectar well
it's two th right it's two it's actually
multiple things because a it's yes we're
not remembering leaves because butterfly
doesn't care about leaves but also uh
what do you do because because um the
the caterpillar is a soft body creature
and the way you move a soft body you
don't have any hard elements to push on
so you can't do robotics the same way
you can't do controlling the same way so
there's a certain set of muscular
motions that you need to do to make your
way over to where the where the leaves
are that isn't going to help the
butterfly the butterfly doesn't move
like that it's got a completely
different architecture and and so so
they have the abstraction there is from
from uh from leaves to food or maybe
even we don't know it might even just be
to um pleasure or something you know
just just positive affectors you know
who knows right um but also but also how
do we make use of that associative
learning that this color leads to food
or to you know to to to pleasure or
whatever um how do we remap that on a
completely different controller and and
you see this even in vertebra it's like
like this is um and actually this was
Doug's Doug's work to
is uh we can make tadpoles with eyes on
their tails and they can see perfectly
well and so it's like isn't that amazing
that with no extra evolutionary Cycles
no no adaptation out of the box this
this thing that for millions of years
had the exact you know the brain could
rely on getting connection from the
visual system into the optic tectum and
all that H Suddenly It's on your tail no
problem it you know connects to the
spinal cord didn't even connect to the
brain it makes it work so what's
happened there do you think how do you
think that what's been remapped what's
been remembered and forgotten I I think
that all of these and there's tons of
these examples that I go through in
various papers is the reason that um
life is so tolerant to these crazy kind
of changes is that it
fundamentally uh assumes the material is
unreliable in other words unlike all of
our computer information the information
the substrate it it assumes that the
substrate is unreliable because look at
this this is how we build our computer
technology you make the bottom layer as
absolutely rock solid as you possibly
can so that all of the stuff on top of
it can assume that everything is going
to go well at the bottom you know when
you write code you don't think your your
your um transistors is going to burn out
you don't worry about that and so so the
goal is to change the to to to to keep
the information from changing and this
is why actually that whole business of
these microchips right how small can you
make a microchip it it's because you
don't want the bits floating when they
get too close to each other they start
to fluct you know the quantum effects
start to fluctuate you don't want that
you want every you want all the bits to
be exactly what they were before you
want Fidelity of the information biology
can't you can't operate that way because
everything is going to change so on a
small time scale your proteins are going
to degrade your cells are going to die
and be replaced on a larger scale you're
going to be mutated right Evolution you
know guaranteed you're going to be
mutated and things will things will
change not just environment but also
your own parts so um I think that there
there may be Exceptions there may be
organisms that aren't like that although
I doubt it I think at this point what
what survived and what what um biology
uh strongly um emphasizes is
architectures where you assume the
underlying material is unreliable and
what you're going to do is on the Fly
you don't overtrain on your priors you
don't assume that the future is going to
be like the past you don't assume you
know what any of your information means
you are going to try to reinterpret it
at the at any given moment on the Fly
and do the best you can and so that
gives rise to uh these kinds of systems
where the eyes in the wrong place we can
we can do something with that basically
right I mean the detail is is it's it's
hard work to figure out okay so um where
is the information actually going you
know it gets onto the spinal cord then
the brain learns to infer some
connection between what the eye says and
what the does it even know it's an eye
I'm not even sure about that so but I
but I think that's what's happening here
is that um biology commits to a realtime
sens making process not to the
expectations of the past you know I
think I think that's the most
interesting part and that's what makes
the stuff so flexible and that's what
makes bio biotechnology possible it
makes you know I'll take my cells and
slap them onto some weird scaffold made
out of crazy nanomaterials and I'll
instrumenti it with electrical signaling
and Optical whatever and things work
because you
know so the so the the butterfly has
solved this problem of um how can I
change and uh and still can I change and
still
exist which I I think I think we all do
I think I mean the butterfly is kind of
an egregious case but but um all of us
have the same problem because over time
we are not the same and you know whether
it be the rearrangements of of of
puberty or just the the you know the
day-to-day wear and tear on the body you
know the the the whole ship of thesias
thing right where where your your
materials are going in and out all the
time um I think I you know I think I
think different species emphasize this
to different extent for example plaria
are the champions of this I mean look
planaria right uh cancer resistant
incredibly regen regenerative uh no
Aging in the asexual forms right no
transgenic lines because they basically
ignore new DNA that you put into them
there are no transic yeah there's no for
people have been trying this since uh I
think since the late 80s people have
been trying to make transgenic planaria
there aren't any no no mutant lines the
only the only lines of aberant plaria
that exist are our two-headed form and
the cryptic form and they're not genetic
it's because the only reason it works is
because it's not genetic uh what
happened in uh in plenaria I think is
that they uh because because they're
they reproduce asexually so they you
know tear themselves in half and
regenerate that means that they
accumulate sematic mutations they don't
clean the genome the way that that we do
with sexual reproduction and so they've
accumulated so much junk that basically
the only way to to have a proper
planarian is to assume the hardware is
is going to be unreliable and to put all
of the effort and we've done
computational models of this actually
and you can see Evolution doing this
when when you get even a little bit of
um regulative competency where the cre
where the creature can make up for
certain subtle defects immediately
Evolution you it's hard for selection to
now see the genomes right because if you
get an animal that looks pretty good do
you look pretty good because your genome
was great or because you actually it's
terrible but you're f fixed it along the
way right and so this is like the stuff
that we see when we make Tates with the
with the scrambled faces and they see
them they they they fix them right so so
what happens is that uh then when
Evolution has a hard time uh selecting
for good genomes all the effort goes
into selecting for more competency which
in turn makes it harder to see the
genome which in turn makes for more and
so you get this you get this thing where
the the pressure on the genome actually
flattens out but the pressure on the
competency keeps rising and so if you
take that all the way way you end up
with plaria that
basically everything went into making an
algorithm which is partially bioelectric
and who knows what else that basically
says I already know my Hardware can't
really be trusted here are all the error
correcting codes and everything else
that we need to do to build a good
planera no matter what happens and then
of course you're insensitive to trans
genes to you know to to cancer all these
things because you're you're you're
you're assuming from day one that all
that stuff can't be trusted right right
you know and I think you know I think I
think so plenaria are kind of all the
way there and then salamanders are
pretty good at it but not as good as
plenaria and then then mammals and then
maybe something like sea elegans or drop
are on the opposite end and they're just
really pretty you know pretty hardwired
maybe uhuh so your when you your
definition of self how far down the
evolutionary ladder does It Go I mean
does it go to single- cell creatures or
they selves or does it uh go or does it
begin at a certain point in evolution
the self as an innovation to to deal
with these problems you're talking about
yeah um I don't I I don't like um binary
categories for any of these things
because they end up chasing us into
these pseudo problems where you can
always come up with these sort of in
between cases and then you spend all
your time trying to prop up this binary
definition as opposed to I I I think I
think what's what allary here between
having a and not having aelf correct
yeah yeah exactly it's on a Continuum I
I think all of it well well yes I think
it's on a Continuum but but the reason
it's on a Continuum is that I take all
of these terms so all of this you know
having a self intelligent sensient you
know cognitive like all the whatever of
these terms you want to use I don't
think they're about the system itself I
think what they refer to is your
intended interaction with it so if you
tell me that you think a certain system
as an observer as a scientist as a okay
as as as a scientist as a as a
conspecific as a parasite as a you know
whatever whatever it's it's every every
agent with living non-living scientific
you know natural whatever you are going
to take some stance towards whatever you
want to interact with and if you want to
take a mechanical stance and say all I
see is a bunch of cogs and gears I'm you
know my the tools I have to interact
with you are just Hardware rewiring well
you know that works well for mechanical
clocks and things like that you try to
apply it to a human if you're an
orthopedic surgeon not bad if you're a
psychotherapist terrible right so so you
know you you want you want an or or or
or a spouse you know terrible you you
want an orthopedic surgeon that thinks
you're a mechanical machine you do not
want dispose or or a psychotherapist
that thinks you're a mechanical machine
so I think all of these things um I
think all of these things uh just just
indicate the frame that you bring to the
interaction and the set of tools you're
going to use and so you got you know you
got your rewiring you've got cybernetics
control theory you know behaviorism
you've got I don't know psychoanalysis
spirituality who know like I'm just you
know sort of drawing the Spectrum right
so so how far down down does it go so uh
that so so what that means is can we get
some sort of utility and that's why I I
harp on the engineering side of this
because I think this should all be
tested by by utility in the in the real
world so so can we get some sort of
utility by applying these Concepts to
single cells absolutely I think yes um
can we apply them to molecular networks
yes within cells I think so we have we
have data on this other people have data
on this could we apply them to uh
particles maybe so I think um Chris
fields and Carl friston and some other
people have done some really nice work
trying to cash out physics as a kind of
uh protoc ogni um substrate like active
I mean they like active inference there
may be some other things um so maybe so
so I was going to ask you too if you
thought this was limited to the realm of
biology I realized friston
doesn't um yeah but I don't know he does
his his work makes a better seems to all
perform better when you transpose it to
the realm of biology then when he starts
talking about active inference and rocks
and crystals and things um but I don't
see the active
piece um well I so so okay yeah you know
I I couldn't possibly repr reproduce the
argument the way the way that he does it
but but I think I think what he's saying
is that um and and and Chris Fields has
has stories about this too which is
basically that there's an equivalency
between um what what is what is a thing
you know what is a rock what is a right
what I mean I think that's a very
important part of the research program
and this idea that there's the active
inference is quite symmetrical when
you're doing something to the
environment the environment is also
learning about you and and so on and I
think the claim there is that there is a
very simple version of this that just
basically looks like physics to us but
if you sort of crank up the the the
relevant parameters then you end up with
things we call life so so so here's
here's what I would say about that um I
I I think when we say biological world
what do we really mean right what what
what's life I I think that what we mean
by life is anything that is good at
scaling up the cognitive light cone that
is anything that um where the hole has a
larger uh is capable of pursuing larger
and more complex goals than the parts
that's what we happen to call life so so
we don't do that for rocks because The
Rock has exactly the same cognitive
light going as as the pieces that go
inside rock it hasn't scaled anything
it's just you exactly the same it's not
more than the sum of its parts in in in
that particular way right so so some
people would do it you know Toni would
do it off of um integrated information
different people do it different ways I
I think it's all about gold directedness
and right I I think it doesn't it
doesn't uh you know you're not going to
find um larger goals that help you deal
with the rock it's basically the same it
follows least action principle that's
about all you're going to get out of it
right right so right so so I think I you
know think biology is what we roughly
call things that are good at it and that
again is a Continuum I think we don't
need to spend any time arguing whether
something is alive or not the real
question is so what's so so what's your
model what what goals do you think this
follows and how does that help you have
a richer interaction with the system and
and what tools can you bring from from
active influence from behavior science
and and and so on I mean look one one
example okay one one recent example is
we showed models of Gene regulatory
Network which are just chemicals you can
might as well be a rock it's just you
know six or seven chemicals interacting
with each other and what we showed is
that if you bring tools from from
Behavior theory meaning meaning
different kinds of learning so
associative conditioning habituation
sensitization you can do some really
interesting things with just with those
networks that have lots of biomedical uh
uh
relevance and and and you know it's
already there you don't you don't need a
cell you don't need any you know you
don't need protoplasma you don't need
any of that just just the mathematics of
having a few uh nodes connected by these
differential equations already give you
a bunch of stuff that we would call
learning and that help you you know and
and and again my goal right remember you
know my goal is not to to do poetry and
to sort of paint hopes and dreams onto
these things and and uh you know that we
could never agree on I I make a very
clear claim that if you know these
things you will do better in the
biomedical Arena than if you pretend
they don't exist and that's that's a you
know that's not a philosophical claim
that's that's an empirical claim that we
can you know that we test you mean as a
scientist or as a creature no as uh well
both uh so so first and is a so so
mostly what I talk about in public is
the science right so so I say as as a
worker in regenerative medicine as
somebody who wants to discover new ways
to use drugs you will do better if you
uh are are able to use the tools of
Behavioral cognitive science on your
cells and tissues than somebody who
doesn't that's that's the first claim
but you could you could push it forward
and say you know in our personal and and
I mean I I have no credentials to be you
know talking about interpersonal you
know social stuff but but but overall it
seems perfectly reasonable to me that we
could apply the same reasoning and say
um the way that uh the the same
pragmatic uh reasoning to our
relationships and say the way I pick
frames for interacting with others is uh
to see how well they work out for me so
purely empirically so so if I treat you
as as you know as an advanced
metacognitive being we can have a
certain kind of relationship and that
elevates me in a certain way uh if I do
something else maybe that doesn't work
out as well if I take one of the lower
you know kind of lower framings so again
just just and it's a way to test it's
it's a way to test the environment too
right you we're going to go in on the
assumption that this is a cognitive
being and we'll see what happens and
we'll see what happens I mean that's the
you know you can you can go the other
way you can say you can start and say
okay I'm going to go on the assumption
that it's not and see what the
limitations are I mean I prefer the
former but but but as long as as long as
everybody's in agreement that this is an
empirical undertaking this is not we
can't we can't just have feelings about
this and this is not something that you
know we're gonna argue about for the
next thousand years and never get
anywhere this this is getting resolved
because you know there's there's clear
data on on a human scale of course it
takes longer right so it takes maybe
years for someone to say you know what
my framing isn't working out for me it's
I'm G to try something different right
that that that may take many years but
right that's kind of What's Happen
happening in the whole field of plant uh
intelligence that people are like let's
let's let's see what happens if we
assume they are cognitive or they have
intelligence uh and some and some you
know some people show that they can
learn some people show they can't um so
taking SS to the the the
human Dimension which I've been looking
at for this chapter I'm working on I've
been talking to neuroscientists and uh
you know people like Anil Seth who's has
written about selves um one of the
things that's curious is especially in
light of what you've uh proposed in this
piece is we're very invested in the idea
of the unchanging
self
um and it's curious we don't embrace the
idea that this is a completely
fungible uh you know subject to our
remaking and our
creativity what why do you think we're
invested in the idea it's it's very hard
to conceive of it I mean in the
definition of self is some continuity
right yeah why do you think we're so
invested in in the idea of a stable
continuous self which you know we're
being told by a lot of different uh
discourses is not
true I yeah I don't know I think uh you
know I can I can make some hypothesis I
I suspect that it's uh it's firmware
left over from our evolutionary past
because if if you were
not um sort of wired to expect object
permanence in the outside world right
you know babies acquired very quickly
and that they have some when they're
born if if if you don't uh if if if
you're not good at seeking out object
permanence and if you're not uh
committed to Persistence of your local
self I suspect that on the Savannah and
whatever the previous versions that are
I suspect that doesn't play out very
well you know uh it's it's not very good
to say I hadn't eaten me liing you know
my my patterns will continue in the
universe in another form like great but
but but my future self will be
undisturbed my future self yeah I have I
have much bigger you know bigger
thoughts than this I don't I suppose
that doesn't work out too well right so
so I can see why why Evolution left us
with some firmware that tries to kind of
dumb it down to this very like basic
survival um for for the same and I think
I think that that firmware has a bunch
of other stuff that needs to be
jettisoned which is which is hard for
example I think a lot of uh the issues
around um you know one reason people
don't like this kind of work right this
this kind of uh diverse intelligence
work is that they worry
about false positives they worry about
too many things being considered as if
they were cognitive and I mean clearly
you can you can make mistakes in that in
that realm I have people that are in
love with Bridges and married to the
Eiffel Tower and stuff like this right
you can that I mean that does happen but
um I think what fundamentally drives
this is a real deep-seated fear and a um
an assumption that there's not enough
love to go around literally like like
like that there's a um uh it's a zero
some game in terms of intelligence and
that if we consider other things to be
to be cognitive in some way well then
mine isn't worth as much you know and
and and again I I I think that's like
ancient scarcity mentality firmware From
Evolution that says no there isn't
enough of anything to go around and
there's status and and it's a zero some
game and if you don't have the status in
your group you know you're screwed and
so that's where I think some of this is
coming from um but this is all you know
that's that's armchair you know armchair
psychologizing I don't know yeah yeah of
course the other reason I mean there are
there are variables you want to keep
steady right and one of the things to
self does is help us with homeostasis
right I mean if you if you use the model
that Seth talks about or some other
people um that we're process we're
always processing signals from our body
and we're looking not to depart from
certain um you know temperature blood
gases I mean there's a whole range of
things that we do want to stay in a very
narrow range well yes and I think that's
the part of this firm that I'm talking
about however um you know from the
perspective of the child's body the
adult body is way off on homeostatic uh
you know homeostatic properties um from
the perspective of the caterpillar the
butterfly you know the butterfly is a
terrible caterpillar like everything is
off you know all of the all of the and
and I think this is true in in in
embryonic development you know from the
from from the perspective of the of the
um the you know gastro the blastula is a
birth effect I in fact I think I
actually think that's how development
works is a it's a set of repairs
activated towards a fast moving Target
morphology which is encoded in bi
electrics and various other things that
basically what happens is you know
you're you're and and we've done we've
done work on this this is going to come
out later later this year we have some
super super cool data around this stuff
that that basically development is a
whole bunch of repairs I'm not even sure
I believe in embryonic development
anymore I think it's all regeneration I
think it's all repair that basically
what happens is your target is your
target moves faster than the an the
anatomy is trying to catch up so the
target information is here the anatomy
is oh my God I'm all wrong and so all
these repair processes kick in and you
make the metamorphosis by the time
you've done that guess what the pattern
has moved on again and and and you're
wrong again so again you have to change
right so it's a set of repair so you
just keep going from stage to Stage
until you catch up and that's adulthood
and you sort of you know maturity and
then you you sort of catch up um and
then and then you get a different issue
with aging but but but you know uh
keeping steady yes but everything is
transformation at least at least until
you hit aging uh everything is
supposedly a positive transformation
right you're trying to you know change
into whatever your next form is supposed
to
be do you think and I'm asking you to to
speculate again there advantages to
giving up on this idea of a stable
self I I I think so I think I think
there are major advantages well uh let's
see one one one advantage is that I
think that it
actually has uh implications for for
ethics of behavior because if if you
can if you if you can sever that um sort
of hardwired link between your current
self and your future
self then one of the things that happens
quite naturally is you start to think
about other beings future selves as
having similar status so so normally you
can be self ficient to the Future in the
sense that well that's still going to be
me but if you can understand that future
self isn't quite the same as your
current self anyway then you say well
for the same reasons I care about this
future self for exactly the same reason
I ought to be caring about other
creatures let that really exist the
future selves right because because
because your future self and all the
hard work you're doing to prop up your
future self in many ways is not as
tightly connected to your current self
as we think and I think breaking that a
little bit would be helpful because then
it would make it it would make it it
would make it seem much more rational to
then be be compassionate to others um
you know right now right now it's very
natural to invest everything in your
future self but once you realize that uh
you know you your your future your
future self is is a different being in
many ways and it's like there there are
there are a number of crazy ways to um
okay like like weird intuition pumps
around this stuff like like here's
here's here's a few examples one thing
that people think about and I I think
this was maybe Anthony flu's argument
about reincarnation he said okay um if I
don't remember if I'm not going to
remember the current life then what's
the difference it might you might as
well just tell me that I'll be dead and
some other kid will be running around
somewhere on Earth and like good but
there's plenty of kids running around on
Earth what do I care and so so he was
trying to say that that memory is is
what keeps it going right and then the
continuity of memory is what keeps it
going but you can imagine things things
like this if somebody says to you are
current self um we're going to uh you
need some surgery and uh you could save
some bucks if you uh if you instead um
instead of having real anesthesia which
you just have as a paralytic so you'll
be paralyzed we can do our thing and in
fact I mean that's a real like that
actually happens to people right that
like it doesn't always work right right
so so uh so then you can save you can
save some bucks um the current self is
going to go well absolutely
not but but but but the fut your self
once you come out of it and they say oh
by the way oh and the other thing to
know is that when you do get the
anesthesia part of the components is a
memory wipe that's a short-term memory
wi that's also a real thing right
because they don't want you remembering
this stuff so so so you come out of it
and somebody says to you you know what
um I think that actually happened uh and
uh and you know and you saved $ thousand
dollars but I think you were actually
there I know you don't remember a bit of
it but you know and at that point you're
like H all right I mean you know now now
now realistically it's an issue because
actually the trauma can can carry
forward but let's just let's just
imagine that you know let's imagine the
memory wipe actually works the future
self will be like yeah I mean fine good
deal right so so there's an inter so so
there's an interesting thing here and
and I think to the extent that we kind
of understand that our future self is is
a construction that is going to sort of
try to make sense of these memories and
whatever I I think it helps you uh be be
kinder to others future C because
they're in the same boat so I think for
that so I think for that reason it's
it's useful I mean it's it's also useful
more broadly because to the extent that
we understand what we are and how we how
the biology works and everything I think
it really helps us have a more ethical
relationship with other other beings
because right now a lot of people uh are
are walking around with this very
magical view of what you know they they
said the humans you know humans do this
and they well which humans you know the
you know 100 thousand years ago you know
a million years ago like which which
humans right and or or during
embryogenesis where does this magic sort
of kick in so so I think having a better
understanding of the biology and what's
actually going on is going to help us
understand that gee there can be other
Minds that are not the con you know the
conventional modern human you know mind
and and help us help us have better
relationships with other systems you
know both both biological and also
synthetic you know artificial all that
kind of stuff yeah I mean it would
probably make us better people but on
the other hand this idea the future self
being continuous that's what gets your
work done right I mean this is going to
I'm I'm embarking I'm writing a book
it's going to take me X years it's going
to be really hard painful but my future
self is going to benefit uh when it
comes out uh you know when I get my
Advance whatever it is um it seems to me
there's a there is some adaptive value
and I mean as you were pointing out on
the Savannah of having a strong sense of
self-continuity
um even though that might make you you
know an yeah yeah no no I think
I mean it's it's true there there there
probably is some competitive survival
value to it I think that um you know
look if okay I I I think back to some
things I've done in the past some some
let's you know some a let's say some
achievements that I've done in the past
yeah I I I and May and maybe it's just
me I I have a um I I find it really hard
to to visualize that that was me like
really like I know I know historically
like if if I look in the record
everybody says it was me and everything
so I know it's me but but but thinking
back I'm like wow uh that's you know
that's amazing I don't remember what it
was like I don't really you know it was
years ago so I don't really remember
what it was like to do it and the
feeling between me having done it and
somebody else having done it is just a
historical record at this point just a
matter of historical record you know I
did things before that I probably
couldn't do now so what does that mean
do I still keep the credit for it it's
you know in in in the soet it Society to
maintain records and to right and to
reinforce these things but but really
you know it's sort of like uh it's been
a long time like do I really you know do
I is it still me that did that I don't
know because I don't think I could do it
again you know that that kind of stuff
so that's so
interesting um I mean to embrace this
idea of self as a as as construct and a
creative act based on interpretation and
misinterpretation of memories it's I
mean it's a very exhilarating idea I
think in many ways in that people are
are very stuck
on uh either the positive case for S
which is a myth or the case against them
which is just demystification without
any sort of positive yeah benefit
there's a you know there's there's
there's an even um well you just just to
to to put put on the radar in case in
case you want to talk about it um there
there's an even weirder if if you think
all of that was weird weird uh the bit
that I only mentioned in that paper that
could that we could talk about is uh uh
erasing the distinction between thoughts
and thinkers because that I think that I
think is even even more of a of a
profound sort of yeah so talk unpack
that a little because you you kind of
raced over that idea and um I think it's
really interesting I mean I I was
actually asking this question I was
talking to anneal and uh I was saying
can you have a a uh a perception without
a perceiver or an inference without an
infer and he was saying yes you can but
I had a lot of trouble getting my head
around that yeah yeah let's uh so let's
and so I so okay so so just to kind of
fair fair warning these these ideas are
pretty new so I'm still kind of chewing
all this around so you know uh take
everything with a with a grain of Sal
but um let's uh I'll I'll start I'll
start with a with a little story uh just
a short this this is a real science
fiction story that I read years ago and
only now I'm sort of understanding the
significance of but I wish I could
remember whose it was I don't I don't
remember uh the deal is that self down
the drain yeah ex exactly right like I
knew at one point I don't know um these
these creatures come out of the center
of the earth they're they're they're
incredibly dense yeah they come out of
the core they're just incredibly dense
they use gamma rays for vision like
super dense so they come up here and uh
everything that you and I see here is
solid it's just gas to them you know
they see they see because because
they're so dense as far as they're
concerned the crust and everything up
everything up here is is a very rarified
kind of plasma around right and so and
so one of them so they have some tool
one of them's a scientist and he's got
some tools and he says to the others he
says you know I've been watching this
gas that surrounds this planet and there
are some uh there's some patterns in
this gas there's some there's some
persistent patterns in this gas and they
look like they're doing things they they
look kind of agentul and so the other
one the others of course laugh at them
and and they say no no look we're real
you know we are actual thinkers you
can't patterns can't be thinkers the
patterns and gas can't be thinkers and
he says no I I'm pretty like it looks
like they're doing things and I've done
some experiments you know and they look
like they have certain cognitive
properties and and then they ask well uh
how long these patterns last well they
only last about a 100 years well that's
ridiculous I mean 100 years what what
could you know what could happen you
know we we live millions of years what
what could happened in 100 years right
so okay so so so right away and you can
sort of take this this further uh you
right away you start to get the idea
that the distinction between a temporary
but somewhat persistent pattern in a
citable medium and a real solid thing
that we you know this is a thing you
know this is the cognizer that's a bit
of in the that's in the eye of the
beholder quite a bit and people who
study metabolics will already say that
of course we're temporary metabolic
patterns that exist in there's flux that
is sort of self you know people who
study um uh uh you know kind of these
these emergent self uh self-reinforcing
energy patterns right that that's that's
how they would describe us anyway so
okay so so once you start thinking about
that um then you can start asking about
further about the distinction between
thoughts as patterns within a cognitive
system and what does it take to spawn
off to have thoughts what does it mean
to have thoughts so once you go down
that road you start to think uh about
imagine this Continuum so here's a
here's a Continuum fleeting thoughts so
these are patterns that come in and
they're gone right persistent intrusive
thoughts so these are thoughts that once
you've had them they are hard to get rid
of and not only are they hard to get rid
of they do a bit of Niche construction
I'm sure you you know all about this is
certain kinds of thoughts actually
change the brain to make it easier to
keep having those thoughts right so so
so they're doing a little bit of Niche
construction they're um PR they're
they're um modifying their environment
to allow themselves to persist and
multiply and and things like that you go
from there and there's there's some kind
of exotic intermediates but the next
thing we for sure know about is um
multiple personality Alters so so not
just a single thought that hangs around
it's like a it's like a bundle of
thoughts that has some Dynamics to it
and can actually you know um do do some
stuff and and then and then of course
there are you know things that we call
full-blown personalities which are like
really consistent uh at least for some
period of time they're consistent sets
of thoughts so so the thing about the
right side of that Continuum is that
these are they they've done two things
one is they've closed the loop in that
they um reinforce themselves so they
right they they prop they they they prop
themselves up over time but the other
thing is that they can spawn off other
thoughts so by the time you get to a to
an altar you've got a you've got a
cognitive um pattern that's complex
enough that can spawn off other simpler
patterns and so now now you try to draw
a distinction between the thought and
The Thinker and it's real hard now
because because okay all we're talking
about is cognitive patterns and some of
these patterns are dissip you know in
the language of dissipative system right
some of them are just you know fleeting
some of them are self-perpetuating like
the red spot of Jupiter and things like
this they sort of keep themselves going
and other patterns uh spawn off smaller
patterns and other patterns hang around
for a hundred years and we give them
names and we you know but don't they
need the I mean but as you suggested
they need the host of of brains right of
I I don't think they well so okay so
this is like very speculative stuff
right so so here we go um first of all I
definitely don't think need brains
because these kinds of things go on in
all sorts of media so they go on in in
protoplasm in nor in cells in in I think
I think there's lots of lots of media
that they can so different substrates
not not necessarily just brains exact
livingres lots of different well we call
the substrate living because it's a
substrate that is capable of Hosting
self-reinforcing goal driven patterns
patterns that have agendas that's what
we call living um but but I think you
could have and I'm sure in the out there
in the universe I'm going to guess
there's all kinds of substrates that are
capable of that um I think we're going
to end up making a whole bunch with with
different um you know both software and
Material Science that people are working
on I don't think there's anything
special about brains per se with for
that aspect but um but here's the here's
the craziest thing and this is just the
latest thing I thought of that I have I
have zero um uh kind of uh details to
back this up but I'll just throw this
out as as a crazy thing uh you know at
the at at the beginning of the 1900s
it was thought that um self-perpetuating
electromagnetic waves so a pattern that
perpetuates for long periods of time
required a material to to be waving you
needed you needed a an an ether that you
could say was something was waving in
order to have a wave right we did we did
away with all that we don't you you can
have a pattern propagating with nothing
waving there you don't need a material
you got rid of The luminiferous Ether uh
because because uh you found out that
the two components the magnetic and the
electric component you know they they
can they can sort of reinforce each
other and and this thing sort of sort of
propagates so I wonder and again I'm not
saying I believe this I'm just saying
this is something I'm toying with at the
moment I wonder if you could make a move
like that you could um get rid of this
cogniferous ether AKA brains or whatever
else and you could have patterns that
are actually self-reinforcing in the
absence of all of that I don't know what
specifically what physical model you
would have I think we need to think more
about this doesn't seem like you need a
physical
model correct the reason correct the
reason you um well the the first thing
that will happen is people say will say
this is dualism and fair or idealism
actually or or idealism yeah fair enough
I I you know I I think that's true and I
think some of the stuff we talked about
before about um the practicalities of
platonic space and those the patterns
that are there like I think this is in
that same in that same vein and I think
yes those things are not physical and
think they're real in the sense that
they make a huge difference about what
happens next and so on um yeah uh the
reason you need some kind of a physical
story at some point is that you need to
flesh out uh a story about the
interaction with physical bodies so what
is it that happens when when Evolution
produces or or an engineer produces some
kind of physical machine what's the
interaction between those patterns that
come to resonate and so so some people
will you know some some somebody will
say incarnate I will say you know you
know Richard Watson will say resonate uh
who knows but but when it comes to when
it comes to these kind of patterns that
are embodied in a physical machine um we
we need some kind of story about about
what happens there because because
otherwise you know they sort of remain
off in this in this so they have to
encounter something they have to yeah
yeah and we're actually doing work so
this is again this is not published yet
um but we're actually doing some stuff
on how you could BAS basically basically
at this point I think that um the the
idea of a of an unchanging permanent
sort of platonic space where everything
just is sort of fixed there I I think
that I think it's much more it's much
more interesting than that I think there
is a chemistry of these things in that
space and I think we have a
computational way to start um doing
experiments there and we have I have a
student working on on some stuff so stay
tuned there will be that it it is it is
completely wild um looking at looking at
agentic properties in sets of logical
sentences just you know just sentences
some of them are passive and some of
them are not some of them do things by
themselves and and it's and it's really
interesting but but that's you know
that's that's that's what I want to um
you know going back to the whole
butterfly caterpillar thing I I think
that you can you can think about this
thing as you've got the left side of
it's it's it's a it's a Bo you know it's
an hourglass SLB tie where right where
you've got um you've got the the there's
Intelligence on the left side that takes
all of these different experiences and
uh generalizes and abstracts to some
sort of compressed engram you've got the
creative intelligent part on the right
side that has to uh reinflated into
whatever the current context is and
figure out what what the what the
memories mean but again all of that that
that first way of telling the story
assumes that the information is passive
and that all the intelligence is on the
is in the hardware what if what if the
data itself is not actually passive what
if these are patterns as as we were just
talking about and patterns that are
using the medium of the physical process
from caterpillar to butterfly right to
to perpetuate and transform themselves
and what if they're doing a bit of um
Niche construction to uh make sure that
they perpetuate and actually you know do
better right as a butterfly you've got
some advantages that that you can have
so so I don't know you know that that
goes back to our um uh the S the the
self- Sorting data in the algorithms
right the the Sorting algorithms where
the distinction between the data and the
and the algorithm is really very much in
the eye of the beholder and and you can
very and if you look for it you can find
the data doing things you know how could
you prove that that there's agency in in
information well the way you prove
agency in anything I think is you show
uh again and this is this is an kind of
an engineering take is you show how
doing so helps you do something new how
how right so so how how does it help you
right it's it's the you know my argument
is that back in the olden days when
people said there's a spirit under every
Rock versus now where the scientists say
there isn't any anywhere both of those
things are wrong because they're just
you have to do experiments and you have
to say here is my theory here's what it
does for me you know I I i' so so what
so so here's what we're doing for this
um uh for the for the uh sorting
algorithms thing what we found and this
was just the first thing we looked for
so no I I got to think there's more but
but we just haven't found it yet the
first thing we found is we found these
algorithms doing stuff that are we that
that that is not explicitly in the
algorithm they are they are doing things
specifically they've they're doing this
clustering behavior that are not in the
algorithm so there are no steps to to do
that in the algorithm now now now in you
know when you're looking at an algorithm
it has a cost to it every computation
costs something so so what we what we
see is that there's an algorithm the
computer's carrying out this algorithm
that you pay you pay an energy toll to
to do all the
but it's also doing something else and
it looks to me like it's doing that for
free so so so here's how I would do it
uh and and I have a I have a somebody in
my lab who's who's who's working on this
right now is to harness that to some
other task that's actually useful
because if you can do that that second
task is getting done for free without
paying an energy uh bill for it now I I
mean obviously that sounds impossible I
understand that and it may well turn out
to be impossible but that's the kind of
thing you you you you have to show an
example where okay I took seriously the
idea that this thing had its own go
directed activity I harnessed that go
directed activity to you know it's like
the donkey with the carrot on the on the
stick right by understanding what what
the drivers of this of this agent are I
can harness it to do useful work and if
I can do more useful work per unit of
cost for compute than somebody else who
doesn't believe in that I mean that's it
there's there's no more to be had than
empirical success so so that's the kind
of thing um that I think we're gonna
have to do that's great that's
fascinating so you need memories to have
a self yes can you have a self without
memory you can have a uh you can have a
self flet you can have you can have a
slice I I you know I do I do think and
this is like going beyond anything that
I can usefully sort of show it's just
the thoughts there that um thin slices
uh are uh they they do have experience
and they probably do have uh you know
some some sort of Consciousness
associated with them but but but if you
don't have carry through then then you
become fleeting thoughts you become a
set of fleeting thoughts basically as
opposed to a coherent reinforcing
pattern right that you could make a
story out of yeah um so you did you just
used the c-word and you used it several
times in this paper um after uh last
time years ago when we met you were
like conspicuously avoiding it um and
there's a really provocative uh sentence
if maybe you could just unpack a little
for me uh could Consciousness simply be
what it feels like to be in charge of
constant self-construction driven to
reinterpret all available data in the
service of choosing what to do
next so tell me how you're thinking
about Consciousness yeah and so and so I
still I still largely avoided because
what I don't have is a full-blown new
Theory Of Consciousness that you know
I'm prepared to defend strongly I'm
working on nobody does well I mean a lot
of people think they do but exactly
right there's there's a lot of people
who are willing to sort of get up with
it get out with it I I'm I don't have
anything like that yet but um but but
but here's here's what did strike me uh
you know um Mark SS whose work on this I
really like uho has this he has this
interesting um point of view that he
thinks that uh he says that
Consciousness is palpated uncertainty
about the future so the idea is that
Consciousness is the is what it feels
like to have to be in charge of knowing
what to do next this idea that right
this so this leads to um connected to
active inference and you know what what
do these patterns mean what can I expect
next how do I minimize my surprise these
things so so so here's another
hypothesis what if um yes all that is
true but there's an even deeper problem
which is that as a conscious agent not
only do you not know what to do next you
don't even know what your own memories
mean you have the constant burden of
having to reinterpret your own memories
all the time and of course it's
subconscious if it was if if this is
something we had to do consciously you
know we wouldn't we would never make it
but it's a little bit like you know
people who um have uh a brain damage and
can't form new memories you know you
wake up in the morning and there's a
there's a there's a notepad next to your
bed and it says hey guess what uh you
can't form new memories here's where
things stand and by the way before you
go to bed tonight write write you know
write write the you know write the next
note and so right so I mean that's what
all of us do but for for all of us that
scratch Pad is internal but for ant
colonies and certain kinds of patients
you have to externalize you have to
externalize those memories somehow so um
I think that uh we we're all kind of in
that boat in that every so many
milliseconds you have to be able to you
have to be you have to reconstruct a
story of who you are what you are what
your plans were right and and and we
don't notice it because it's I mean it
has to be automatic otherwise we notice
it when we wake up in the morning yeah
there there's an interesting moment of
reconsolidation of self yep yep there is
and and I wonder if I wonder if the this
is the problem with trying to make sense
of our dreams too is that and and I'm
not I'm no no expert on dreams but but
but I wonder if part of the issue is
that at night you don't really do a
super
good job of memories in a way that your
future self is going to decode them and
that that's the the crazy Dre where you
can't even figure out what what the heck
it was it's basically because you're
looking at these an Gams going I can't
make heads of taals of this and and it's
just it's just more difficult than than
than waking you know waking memories I
don't know that that's that's a
hypothesis but I wonder you know for
Consciousness I I I think that I think
Mark is right but I also think that
there's an even deeper task facing uh
selves you know conscious selves which
is that you can't even you can't even
really rely on the past it's uh you know
you have to you have to reconstruct it
all the time you have to figure out what
you are and re you know recommit to
being an agent doing things so that that
was that was my hypothesis yeah I think
it's a fascinating idea of course and we
haven't talked about the social world
but that that is helping us in a funny
way and and constraining us right I mean
you're being told who you are all the
time by the people around you you know
who who kind of keep you in certain
roles yeah and limit that your ability
to change um yeah there's there's a
softening of self that happens when
you're not in a social environment it
seems to
me so I I thought about this too with
regard to psychedelics which have
interesting effects on the self and on
memory um all sorts of stuff comes up
people people talk about a period of ego
dissolution a complete loss of sense of
self yet they're still conscious um and
then this kind of putting things
together in a new way you know I mean
especially with the trauma victims are
treated um they uh they take out their
memories difficult memories and when
they reconsolidate them they're not the
same um they've got they've lost the
emotional charge or whatever it is I
mean there's a kind of very interesting
process of playing with your memories in
psychedelic experience so that you end
up being a slightly different self when
you come out if it's working I mean
that's kind of the theoretical model is
is get you out of your habitual ways of
looking at things and you're and and
those kind of uh you know rumination I
mean those sort of the thoughts you were
describing that take up resonance in
your brain that you might not
necessarily
want that's super interesting and I
wonder if uh there is a clinical um path
here by taking seriously the idea that
some of those thoughts may not want to
leave like literally right you know and
and there may be some that is trauma I
mean that's you know part of trauma yeah
yeah but but but I wonder if you know
taking taking serious vious ly their
ability to process
information maybe not in the same way as
a full-blown altar but but but still not
passive data but actually a pattern that
can you know a A dissipative system that
can actually process information you
know it may I mean I don't I don't know
anything about this so so maybe this is
totally nuts but I've heard U various
kinds of um alternative therapists and
whatnot you know wanting you to talk to
your different know this but but so so
that may not be in that may not be crazy
there
right there may if if they can if these
patterns can process information to some
extent there may be stimuli you can give
them where where basically you're not
you're not just treating the brain to
somehow take care of this Al that may
work too but you're actually maybe maybe
maybe there is something to be set for
communicating well yeah this is now this
is the theory in treating schizophrenia
you know yes you are hearing voices why
don't you talk to them or why you let me
talk to them um and if you think about
it trauma
memories of trauma do process
information because you get you know you
hear a gunshot or something now and it's
processed as that uh or a siren or
whatever it is so they are still active
in your brain in an interesting way
yeah yeah that's very that's very
suggestive um I'm Gonna Let You Go in a
sec I just have one or two more
questions
um well this kind of relates to that
psychedelic point but it's interesting
that we we cherish ourselves and we talk
about um self-esteem and building up the
self you know with our kids
um and we're very wetted to the idea of
as I said earlier this this unchanging
enduring self yet at the same time we
spend a lot of effort trying to
transcend it and Escape ourselves um
whether it's through drugs is one way
but also um travel uh experience
awe that we know kind of diminish the
self religion giving yourself over to
the group why do you think we also want
to transcend
selves I think again I I don't know but
I think that probably there are
competing drive so so there's the
there's The evolutionary firmware that
says uh defend yourself at all costs
right that's I think that's got to be in
there but there may well be an opposing
component that says yes but if you stand
still you're also not going to make it
so it's like um you know with active
inference there's this thing you you
know surprise minimization right so but
but the easiest way not to be surprised
is to stick your head in the corner and
not look at anything and then there will
be one final surprise at the end when
somebody eats you but that's it until
then you're not surprised so you know so
so there's got to be I think in biology
there's got to be two competing drives
one is surprise minimization one is
exploration where it says you know if
you haven't seen anything new in a long
time you might be stuck in a corner you
better do something else right and so so
maybe it's something like that maybe
it's like yes defend yourself but also
if you're too stuck and you haven't
learned anything new and you haven't
improved and you haven't whatever then
um and and I don't know if that's
something that's uh comes from the
biology itself or meaning just you know
a drive with actual um selective
advantage or whether that's sort of a
consequence of being an advanced being
uh that you know has some sort of semis
spiritual drive to um to improve over
time or something right right you
familiar with the D this is another
binary between exploring and exploiting
yeah um it kind of reminds me of that
idea that there is a desire I mean we
spend a lot of time in exploit mode as
adults um but we also need to do the
exploration and that and that's the
exploit mode has the strongest sense of
self yes um psychologists would say yeah
yeah yeah I think that makes sense and
and I wonder if I wonder if aging on the
cellular level if aging is is a part of
that you know well you chase you chase
the the the moving Target morphology as
an embryo and eventually you reach your
adult form and sort sort of that's it
you've caught you've caught up and so
now the name of the game is to defend
against tiny local um defections of
cancer and degeneration and and just you
know cells getting old and so on but but
but if once you've given up uh once
you've given up that you're on a
trajectory for some kind of construction
project maybe that you know that that's
it if you if you're if you're stuck in a
rut of exploit and you're really not
exploring anything that may be when
things start to go to pot I I don't know
I mean you know the the the kind of uh
familiar folk example is you know the
people who who retire from from their
job and then immediately drop dead right
so that's the right that that's just
kind of a but but maybe something like
that is going on um on a on a on a
cellular level where basically you know
uh when there's nothing pulling you
there there is no more of that uh the
forces which is what we study during
development that pull you from stage to
stage at that point then then then
things things start to go downhill I
don't know yeah um I noticed in your um
acknowledgements which was a fascinating
list I read it um Bernardo castr was in
there yeah tell me about I'm talking to
him tomorrow I've never met him oh yeah
yeah we've yeah we've had a i' I've had
a couple of conversations with with
Bernardo um online and you know a bunch
off uh yeah super interesting dude um
computer science uh kind of background
philosophy um you know he's got this
kind of idealist model um yeah I think
he's very interesting I you know he did
a he did a cool uh session with rert
spir and they sort of talked about this
notion of uh all of us being
dissociative altars of the great Cosmic
mind and things like that um yeah I I I
think you'll have fun I think he's he's
he's a very smart guy I think you'll
have fun I I find I'm reading his book
right now he has a new book that he sent
me a copy of um the epistemology piece
seems very persuasive I mean the more we
learn about active inference and the
fact that we're constructing our
perceptions are limited by our cognitive
equipment and the world we're seeing is
mental to a greater extent than we
realize um but then he goes to the next
step that what's really there is mind
and that's I don't understand that he
sort of asserts it without arguing it um
well he's got he's got I think five
other books that yeah I know he's
probably leaning on and I'm not I'm not
going to try to um kind of make his
argument for him because I think I'll
butcher it he he'll he'll do a much
better job of it himself you can ask him
to just like say it but uh you know I I
think that
fundamentally I I I I like that idealist
position in the sense
that I I think what actually propagates
through Evolution Through the Universe I
I think the the fundamental um pieces
are are perspectives so I I don't think
it's genes I don't think it's bodies I
think it's um I think it's uh I think
it's perspectives and so well what I
mean is that that any any agent uh you C
you can't afford to um you can't you
can't afford to try to see the world as
it is in the sense of like a lassan
demon you can't afford to track micro
States because if you if you try to
track micro states by the time you
figure out what's going on you'll be
long dead any any biological system that
in in the real world has constraints of
energy of time uh so so what that means
is you're going to core screen you're
going to decide what am I ignoring what
am I paying attention to I'm going to
take all these kinds of observations and
I'm just going to lump them all together
and I'm going to call you know and I
don't mean this is not just humans doing
this is every cell every bacterium
everything's doing this so what you
really have there then is a perspective
it's a commitment to it's a set of
choices that say here's what I'm paying
attention to and here's um uh how I make
sense of it here's what I think it means
you know it's a it's a it's an
interpretation so so that's what I think
is perpetuating through the universe and
being selected on and you know altering
with time and all that is is a set of
perspectives a set of a particular
vantage point of saying here's how I
make sense of my world and and once we
understand that that every cognitive
being is limit every finite every real
being is finite we're all limited we all
have to choose a perspective that
ignores all kinds of other stuff and
it's not just about only being able to
sense a small um narrow band of the
spectrum it actually I mean that's true
too but but it's much more than that
it's cognitively not just perceptually
that we're
limited uh then I think uh you know then
then yeah then it's then it's all about
uh what we're are you talking about
perspectives in the in the in the minds
of living things or are you talking
about perspectives at large I'm talking
about perspectives I mean I I we can
talk about what living things are but I
think that any agent that has to whether
we would call it living or not I mean
any any kind of robotic thing any kind
of a uh system that solves problems in
in a world of some sort is going to have
to have a perspective on that world and
the more right for a rock you don't
worry too much about its perspective
although you with potential energy and
things like that you almost kind of get
there but but but for most things things
that have a significant inner
perspective we call those things living
typically but doesn't have to be uh and
and yeah and whatever World they you
know you can you can ask like Gene
regulatory networks what's the world
that they navigate it's not the physical
threedimensional world it's the it's a
high-dimensional transcriptional space
that they live in and I think from that
P from from no pun intended from that
perspective what you put what what ends
up being emphasized a lot more is what
choices are you making about your uh
cognitive um uh framing of your world
and a lot less about some uh objective
World existing out there somewhere and
uh yeah I think I think that's how you
get to idealism is just is just by
recognizing that all
um uh real real agents are going to be
finite and limited therefore what you're
really talking about is uh an inner
world that you're building for yourself
it's it's your own self model that's
that's that's at play here not not some
objective thing and that your self model
May or your model of the world may or
may not be compatible with mine um you
know yeah so in your view though I'm I'm
assuming something but I could be wrong
um the prerequisites of self and the and
and the process you're describing do you
think that that can be embodied in a
computer
yes but computer has to I mean again
whether something in a is a computer is
in the eye of the beholder what what
what we what what we mean when we say
something is a computer is that I have a
set of uh conceptual tools that I bring
to the table here that come from
computer science and I'm claiming that
those tools are useful that that's all
that's all it means and um do I think
that uh some of those tools are useful
to understand cognition yes you know for
example reprogrammability and software I
think it's extremely useful uh do I
think the vanoyan architecture and the
sharp distinction between data and the
Machine are particularly useful no I
think we'll have to dump those uh do you
know do I think that at some point we
could make synthetic uh beings that have
the right features absolutely I don't
see any reason why uh it it see it seems
completely backwards to me to say that
the the blind uh meanderings of The
evolutionary process can create real
minds but but but intelligent Engineers
who understand how minds work can't do
it that that seems crazy to me so so I I
think that that for sure once we
understand and I think we're getting
there I think we understand you know a
few of the key features um I I don't see
any reason why we couldn't uh
reimplement them in a synthetic
substrate sure yeah but you need a
substrate that as youve said is not at
all like a van v noyman
correct correct I yeah I think you need
a number of things and the and the thing
is that um I I started I started WR
those things down I started writing a
paper this was months ago I started
writing a paper to say look these are
the things we've learned from biology if
you just do these things you will have
you know a real a real agent and then
then I stopped and and although I don't
think this is going to solve it because
somebody else will of course do it but I
didn't want to be responsible for it
because I think that to whatever
extent that's on the right track it may
not be but but if it is then what that
means is that it makes it very easy to
make trillions of other beings that are
have um that have more that deserve
moral consideration and I'm not really
interested in being the cause of that
but I'm sure that's where we're going
I'm sure I'm sure this will get figured
out and this is what will happen yeah
other people are working on it oh yeah
including including Mark Zs by the way
yes yes that's that's right that's right
and I would very simplistic and it's and
it's using you know computers as as they
now exist yeah I think that um I think
of of of anybody's uh project that uh
that I think has a chance of doing
something like that I think his is at
the top of the list I actually think he
could do it yeah amazing
amazing well thank you are you writing a
book a g a trade book uh I am uh I'm
currently um on Pagan and I are writing
a book on
bioelectricity and uh it doesn't it
doesn't have any of this stuff in it
it's just straight up bioelectricity uh
but the next book if I you know if I if
I uh get there uh the next book will be
all of this stuff basically great
Evolution cognition all that stuff and
are you going to do that for a general
audience I don't you know I don't know I
I'm I'm still we're still um so so
Richard Watson and I are probably going
to do it together or or maybe we'll do
two books we we haven't been able like
maybe it'll be two books back toback or
something we'll have you know maybe
inverted like the way that uh um uh it
was done for the planaria journal and
and and all that uh I don't I don't know
um I I'm I'm having a really hard time
figuring out what what is the best thing
to do here because on the one hand I
could do a book for for a general
audience and I think what would happen
then is that a lot of these there there
will be a set of people from let's say
the alternative sort of um you know new
age kind of community who would read
these things and they say oh yeah no
kidding we we we've known this for a
long time and we you know they don't
they don't need you know they don't need
um you know scientific you know sort of
experiments to prove it whatever they
they're already in in for it um and then
there will be the science Community who
will say well there's not enough uh meat
here to convince me of any of these
crazy things right so so I so I worry
about that issue for the tradebook you
know um I it sounds like that could miss
uh the impact on the other hand on the
other hand if we do a you know an
academic press book where you where you
go into detail on on all of this stuff
uh yeah I'm not you know I'm not sure
I'm not sure which of my colleagues have
time to read something like that uh you
know who who's read it I don't know so
so I still haven't figured out what the
right I mean I think you've got a really
interesting book around some of these
ideas and um uh I think it'd be of
interest to a lot more than new age
people um I really do um do you have a
literary agent I do yeah I do yeah um I
mean it's a conversation to have with
that person is it who is it brockman's
shop or it is yeah yeah yeah Dan
introduced me to Brockman yeah yeah yeah
we'll have a I mean I mean he obviously
wants a trade book all right so um now
the other thing is you know they don't
which which is kind of wild they don't
like um images and they certainly don't
like color I have I have some amazing uh
color illustrations and I don't know
that feels weird to me in this modern
day and age with computer like do we
even need a book I couldn't I just put
it all on a website like why do we need
a book I don't you know you know and
somebody's gonna tell you not to use
color like I don't know yeah um yeah
well good luck with that I I I just
think that these ideas would be of
interest to a lot of people in a lot of
different fields they're very
interdisciplinary ideas and um so uh I
think the right trade book would reach
your colleagues or colleagues and other
you know in philosophy and computer
science um anyway it's all it's just
fascinating stuff well thank you I
appreciate that I'll I'll be in touch
because because I will definitely want
to pick your brain when it comes time
happy too I'm happy to read a proposal
if you do that or whatever kind of
suggestions um that be super useful
thank you good and I'm gonna be in
Cambridge this fall so uh I'll look you
up we can get together in person
definitely yeah we'll hang out